<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Always Be Learning</title>
    <description>The technical blog of Britney Wright. Emphasis on Ruby, Ruby on Rails and front-end development. Also other things, because I said so.</description>
    <link>http://alwaysbelearning.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://alwaysbelearning.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Steel City Ruby</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; src=&quot;/../assets/2014/08/steel_city_collage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steel City collage&quot; /&gt;
This past weekend I attended &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steelcityruby.org/&quot;&gt;Steel City Ruby Conf&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, PA. It was my first programming conference outside of the DC area so I was a bit nervous, but also excited to visit another community. And the benefits of community ended up being the biggest takeaway I got from the conference. Unlike other conferences I’ve been to, SCRC wasn’t filled with all technical talks. Sure there were a few, but there were also a lot of talks that, in my opinion, were related to our relationship with programming. Each speaker brought their own set of experiences and background to the group which not only provided fresh perspective, but also helped me fuel an internal dialogue about what matters most to me. I won’t do a recap of all of the talks, but I will touch on the ones that I found the most compelling personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;remembering-scrc14&quot;&gt;Remembering SCRC14&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jean Lange, one of the organizers of SCRC and the MC for the event, opened the conference with a retrospective about the conference. It was highly atypical of a conference opening and really planted a seed for how I took in everything I experienced over the weekend. Jean talked about setting long and short term goals and asked us to think about what we could do over the course of the weekend to work towards those goals. She provided her own example of looking forward and looking back by stating the goal she made a year ago for SCRC14 and what she did over that year so that by the time the conference started her goal was realized. I didn’t write down her goal and I don’t want to misstate it, so I’ll just say it was about having a diverse and open conference. And to achieve that she set goals over the course of the year including creating a code of conduct, providing clear information, promoting the call for proposals, etc. I think it all goes back to one of my favorite habits of Stephen R. Covey, author of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Seven-Habits-Highly-Effective-People/dp/406204983X/ref=la_B000AQ2VAQ_1_21?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1408452003&amp;amp;sr=1-21&quot;&gt;The 7 Habits for Highly Affective People&lt;/a&gt;. Covey’s second habit is Begin with the End in Mind. When we do this we are better able to comprehend how what we’re doing in the present and near future will effect our more distant future. This also helps us adjust course when we realize that what we’re doing isn’t on the path to our intended destination. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking a lot about what I want out of work and although I still haven’t narrowed it down specifically I do know that I want to work in a team. Not just any team, a great team of people who are proud of their work. I’ve been plagued by this constant inability to find a job that places a strong importance on team. Don’t get me wrong, I’ve worked with some great people. And I’ve been proud of my work. But I’ve never felt like I was really part of a team, just one of a bunch of people who happen to be in close proximity and working for the same company. I decided I’d spend the conference connecting with people and talking with them about what they do, where they work, what the environment is like. It was really insightful and has motivated me to pursue that line of questioning more often so I can get a better sense of the variety of places that are out there and what’s most in line with my wants and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;saving-the-world-with-ruby&quot;&gt;Saving the World with Ruby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually already heard this talk by &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/seanmarcia&quot;&gt;Sean Marcia&lt;/a&gt; at Arlington Ruby a few months back, as he was preparing to give it at Rails Conf in Chicago. He talked about how he used Ruby, Sinatra and Raspberry Pis to help study bees at George Mason. Sean is such a great storyteller and he brought honey this time! Beyond the programming aspect he did a great job of showing how we as programmers should seek out opportunities to do work for a greater good than our day jobs typically allow and how we can get support from our employers in those efforts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-ruby-for-journalism&quot;&gt;Using Ruby for Journalism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/derekwillis&quot;&gt;Derek Willis&lt;/a&gt;, of the New York Times, shared how programming has come to be a crucial part of news organizations for research, reporting and randomness. By randomness I mean the experimental projects Derek’s colleagues have created like &lt;a href=&quot;http://haiku.nytimes.com/&quot;&gt;Times Haiku&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/newsgraphics/2013/09/13/fashion-week-editors-picks/&quot;&gt;Front Row to Fashion Week&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2008/02/23/movies/20080223_REVENUE_GRAPHIC.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;The Ebb and Flow of Movies: Box Office Receipts 1986-2008&lt;/a&gt;. Beyond the fact that it made me realize what brilliant minds work at the Times, it also illustrated how fostering a creative, collaborative work environment can produce innovative work. If a newsroom under constantly tight deadlines and battling old school ways of thinking can produce stimulating work then I think I owe it to myself to find a an environment that fosters that as well.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-metaphysics-of-strings&quot;&gt;The Metaphysics of Strings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gregates&quot;&gt;Greg Gates&lt;/a&gt; is a teacher, philosopher and programmer and so it’s no surprise that his talk took on a much deeper meaning than simply comparing two strings. Greg broke down how we can look for and understand the underlying layers in a line of code. He also described how after determining why two lines of code looked the same but were different he wasn’t sure if they should be different or not. And it’s at this level that you know you are truly reading and understanding code at a deep level. This is important to me especially when I’m stuck on something and ask for help from others. Often times a more experienced programmer will brush off those rare programming anomalies by either saying, “don’t worry about that”, or “do this instead.” It’s not for me to say whether they understand what’s going on or not, but Greg made me realize there’s really value in taking the time to dig deeper and understand rather than making assumptions or dismissing something all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dealing-with-the-demands-of-the-open-source-community&quot;&gt;Dealing with the Demands of the Open Source Community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sethvargo&quot;&gt;Seth Vargo&lt;/a&gt;’s talk felt like a therapy session, at least ones I’ve seen on TV since I haven’t gone to therapy yet. He started by identifying the emotions we feel when our open source work is criticized. Then he dove deeper into the root of those feelings and finally what we can do to create a better dynamic with those who consume our projects. I liked the fact that at the end Seth brought his talk full circle and said that while it’s understandable to feel the way we do we still need to keep in mind the person on the other end consuming our product and how we can make them feel if we are critical back, particularly in a much larger open forum like social media. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lightning-talks&quot;&gt;Lightning Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 100%; display: block;&quot; src=&quot;http://bukk.it/mindblown.gif&quot; alt=&quot;mind blown&quot; /&gt;
The lightning talks were all great and so different from one another. The first was How to Find GIFs by &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/nqrush&quot;&gt;Nick Quaranto&lt;/a&gt;. He flew through his talk with storm force speed and energy. First he talked about sites where you can find GIFs, obvious ones like Buzzfeed (don’t use Buzzfeed) and some not so obvious ones like Reddit. Then he showed us the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ifttt.com/recipes/141781-save-hot-posts-in-r-gifs-to-gifs-folder-in-dropbox&quot;&gt;IFTTT recipe&lt;/a&gt; he uses to automatically save GIFs into a Dropbox folder, which has over 6GB of GIFs!. And finally he showed us how to make our own GIFs by using our web cam and &lt;a href=&quot;http://gifbrewery.com/&quot;&gt;GIF Brewery&lt;/a&gt;, a GIF converter. I’ve stayed away from using GIFs for one reason or another, but his enthusiasm and information have made me reconsider. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a more serious level, the lightning talk by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/laurenvoswinkel&quot;&gt;Lauren Voswinkel&lt;/a&gt; about openly discussing your pay has caused me to do a lot of deeper reflecting. I don’t go around shouting my salary from the hilltops, but if anyone has ever asked how much I’m making I’m always willing to share it. I rarely ask others though because there does seem to be a general stigma about it. Either employers discourage it, or maybe people are afraid that they’ll start talking and discover big pay differences that could lead to resentment, power shifts, etc. I, like Lauren, believe that knowledge is power though. I didn’t talk to people about salaries before I interviewed for my current job, and as a result I think I’m making a lot less than I could be. That’s definitely a mistake I won’t make in the future. I’ll also encourage others to be open about it as well since our roles as developers are in such demand, there’s no reason that we shouldn’t be compensated adequately. But as a new programmer eager to work it can be easy to get taken advantage of, particularly in the age of startups and bootstrapping. I also learned a couple of things I hadn’t realized before. You are not required to tell potential employers what you made at your previous job if they ask. Also there are no laws that explicitly bar employees from discussing pay with one another and there are laws that prevent employers from retaliating against employees that do. There are nuances to these laws including the definition of an employee, so it’s best to do a little reading up if you aren’t sure. Lauren shared a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2014/07/when-the-boss-says-dont-tell-your-coworkers-how-much-you-get-paid/374467/2/#comments&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on her Twitter account by the The Atlantic that seems like a good intro to the topic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;better-visualizations-with-science&quot;&gt;Better Visualizations with Science&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 100%; display: block;&quot; src=&quot;/../assets/2014/08/apple_pie_chart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;mind blown&quot; /&gt;
The part that most stuck with me of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jxxf&quot;&gt;John Feminella&lt;/a&gt;’s talk was the anti-patterns he pointed out in data visualizations. Things people do that make data unclear or deceptive and should be avoided (unless you’re just a deceptive SOB I suppose). Things like tilting pie charts, adding volume to them and color choice can make smaller variables appear larger than variables that are actually larger. It was a good reminder as a consumer of information to really make sure I’m looking at what’s being presented and also what’s not being presented. Data visualizations are really what someone has extracted out as important to them. It’s up to us to go from there to find out more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;from-dev-to-founder&quot;&gt;From Dev to Founder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/brynary&quot;&gt;Bryan Helmkamp&lt;/a&gt; from Code Climate presented a very clear path to starting a company and did so in an informative and humorous way. I’m sure everyone’s heard a million tips and talks about starting a company so I’ll quickly summarize a few of the points still lingering in my mind from the talk. Bryan recommends starting a business-to-business company that produces recurring revenue of $67 on average per customer. B2B isn’t as complicated as B2B2C or as hard to generate sizable revenue as B2C. Starting off with a revenue model helps to keep you motivated to keep working on the business. And if you can get your first 150 customers paying $67 a month each on average you’ll earn $10,000 a month which can be enough to provide you the equivalent of a full-time salary. So really it’s just a matter of finding the idea that can fall in line with all of those things and the money should roll in, right? Probably not that simple, but definitely a good reminder of the KISS method. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-lightning-talk&quot;&gt;My Lightning Talk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; src=&quot;/../assets/2014/08/rails_girls_talk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rails Girls Lightning Talk&quot; /&gt;
I, along with my Rails Girls Summer of Code partner &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/justjamonit&quot;&gt;Jam&lt;/a&gt;, gave my first lightning talk at a conference. We provided some information about Rails Girls and Rails Girls Summer of Code and also talked about our personal experiences with both. We received lots of positive feedback on our talk. Even better though were the conversations that followed with people from all different places who wanted to know more about what we were doing with Rails Girls in the DC area and what they could do to grow and engage people in their own communities. I haven’t been at this that long but it felt so good to be able to make suggestions and reference what I’ve seen and experienced. Hopefully I’ll get invites to some new Rails Girls workshops in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hearts-people&quot;&gt;♥ People&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 49%;&quot; src=&quot;/../assets/2014/08/pnc_people.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pittsburgh panorama&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 49%;&quot; src=&quot;/../assets/2014/08/games.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pittsburgh panorama&quot; /&gt;
Once again my voice was shot by the end of the weekend from all the talking I did. It’s a great feeling since I spend most of my 9-5 in silence in my cubicle. I think I only received one business card and I actually kind of liked that. I was able to float in and out of conversations and just chat with people without feeling like I had to prove myself to anyone. I now know about communities that are not too far that I can visit on occasion and also communities that are very far but will have familiar faces if I’m able to venture to them one day. I wish I could list every single person I had the pleasure of talking with and all the organizers who put on such a great conference. Technically I could, but that would take a lot of time and we all know most people leave when movie credits start rolling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hearts-pittsburgh&quot;&gt;♥ Pittsburgh&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; src=&quot;/../assets/2014/08/pittsburgh_pano.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pittsburgh panorama&quot; /&gt;
This weekend was my first time visiting Pittsburgh and I now have a major crush. The city has so much character. I was mainly in the North Shore area where the conference was held at the New Hazlett Theater and also where I stayed in a charming row house (thanks airbnb). Downtown is right across the river, where I had a couple of meals. We also spent the after (first day of the conference) party in the suite level of PNC Park. The ballpark was beautiful although I’m not sure everyone was as excited as I was about the venue. In fact one person told me he’s lived in the Pittsburgh area his whole life and has never attended a Pirates game. Mind blown. After the conference I did some sightseeing on my own. I visited the Andy Warhol Museum which continued to reinforce the idea that I should push myself to do things I love and that challenge me creatively. I checked the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.duquesneincline.org/&quot;&gt;Duquesne Incline&lt;/a&gt; off my Pittsburgh must-do list and made it to the Strip District to see the different markets and vendors. It makes the markets in DC look like so inadequate. And because I have a love of all things thrift and salvage I found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.constructionjunction.org&quot;&gt;Construction Junction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://pccr.org/&quot;&gt;Pittsburgh Center for Creative Reuse&lt;/a&gt; and bought a few odds and ends.
&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; src=&quot;/../assets/2014/08/salvage_haul.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;salvage haul&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anybody asks I’ll tell them Steel City Ruby is the best conference I’ve been to. The talks were great, the people were great, the venue was great. Here are my final quick thoughts about the conference: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The conference pretty much ran on schedule the entire time. If there were delays the schedule had enough breaks throughout that the organizers were able to keep things on track.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organizing committee. There were so many organizers and it showed, not only because of the yellow shirts they wore throughout the conference, but also in how smoothly everything seemed to run.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Single track ftw. I much prefer the single track conference to multi-track conferences. I didn’t have to contemplate what I wanted to listen to at different times and it was easy to just start talking about a specific session with someone because we all listened to the same talks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open dev space. Since the conference took place at a theater the organizers set up the back stage area as a dev space for people to work on things, chat (quietly), or just take breaks when needed. Another benefit of this space was the instruction to only use the wifi in that area. I think this curbed the use of laptops during talks so the people in the audience were giving speakers more of their attention than I’ve seen in other conferences. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swag attack. I lost track, but I think I left the conference with about five or six new shirts. I don’t want to name names but I definitely know some people that left with more than 10 shirts. My favorite item that I picked up though was a brochure from the Pittsburgh based company 4 Moms. It was about their dev team and I really liked it because it listed out their stack and also diagrammed their work flow of choice. Other companies could benefit from something informational like that rather than just sending their HR people with stickers and shirts, in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not conference related, but my some of my new friends from Philadelphia have a podcast called &lt;a href=&quot;http://turing.cool/&quot;&gt;Turing-Incomplete&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a round table format on various programming topics. It’s very conversational and easy to listen to, so check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://alwaysbelearning.com/2014/08/19/steel-city-ruby/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alwaysbelearning.com/2014/08/19/steel-city-ruby/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ruby for Good</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 100%&quot; src=&quot;/../assets/2014/08/teampathwayhomes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Team Pathway Homes group photo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past weekend I attended &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rubyforgood.com&quot;&gt;Ruby for Good&lt;/a&gt; in Fairfax, VA. It also happened to be on the campus of my current employer, George Mason University. The intent of Ruby for Good was to work on projects that benefit others. It was just what I needed. A break from my usual lone wolf-ness and a chance to work in a team environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to call Ruby for Good a conference, because although it was a gathering of a large number of people and there were talks, it wasn’t talking heads the whole weekend. I also wouldn’t call it a hackathon. Yes some teams built applications, but that wasn’t the end-goal. Ruby for Good felt most like a retreat. We stayed in the dorms over the weekend and used different spaces around campus to work on our projects, listen to talks, dine and socialize. It was as much about building as it was about learning and collaborating. The term “growing your network” is pretty cliche at this point, but Ruby for Good attracted people from as far away as Canada and Atlanta so it really was a great opportunity to get to know people outside of our local community. I also think there’s a bit of self selection that goes into attendance at an event like this, so the atmosphere over the weekend was very friendly and open. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I spend most of my day working in a very quiet office with no other developers this was a great opportunity for me to code on a team. I joined a project for a local non-profit, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pathwayhomes.org/&quot;&gt;Pathway Homes&lt;/a&gt;. Pathway Homes provides affordable housing for the mentally disabled. We built a maintenance request ticket system for them so they could keep better track of repair requests that come in from tenants and property managers. My team was very large, and in most cases that might be cause for concern with so many different viewpoints. But our team chemistry was great. We took time initially to make sure we fully understood the needs of Pathway Homes. We also mapped out the primary work flow and application architecture before dividing the work up amongst the team. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built the application with a Rails back-end and a Frankenstein style Rails/&lt;a href=&quot;https://angularjs.org/&quot;&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt; front end. Since most of us hadn’t used Angular before we didn’t have enough time to create a pure single page Angular front-end. I worked on the service requests index view and also helped with some of the styling. My contribution was small in the scheme of all the work that went into the application, but the opportunity to learn Angular for the first time with people around to answer questions was good and now I know why people are so enthusiastic about it. I didn’t have time to dive deep into the framework, but my favorite part was how easy it is to set up filtering. That’s something I always need in the Rails applications I start but then I get overwhelmed with all the different filters I need and how to set them up. With AngularJS it was so simple to set up a search box that would search through all the tickets on the index page. Just two bits of code in the index and a little more code in the Angular controller and the whole thing was working. I can’t wait to go over it more and see how I can add it to a couple of old applications I’ve started that are very data focused.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only downside to the entire event was the sadness that came at the end, knowing that I have to go back to working alone. But it was really incredible to see that in less than three full days we developed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pathway-homes.herokuapp.com/&quot;&gt;fully functional application&lt;/a&gt; that Pathway Homes can start using. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about our working process in a little more detail. By the time we demo-ed the application on Sunday afternoon we had over 400 commits and over 40 closed issues. We used Github for the project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alindeman/pathway-homes&quot;&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt; and made the brave decision to just push changes directly to master, while constantly pulling to try. Since most of us weren’t working on the same files at the same time we didn’t have a high rate of merge conflicts. There may have been an incident or two, like me deleting the application controller. But I put it back! I never program with other developers so it took me a little bit to get down the steps I needed to correctly add my changes without conflicts. We also used &lt;a href=&quot;https://waffle.io/alindeman/pathway-homes&quot;&gt;Waffle.io&lt;/a&gt; which put all of our Github issues into a virtual kanban so we could quickly see what still needed to be worked on and how things were progressing. This was especially useful since we were all working on small parts and allowed us to see how the ship was moving overall and where someone could jump in if they finished something they were working on. We also used &lt;a href=&quot;http://hipchat.com/&quot;&gt;HipChat&lt;/a&gt; to share links and communicate when we weren’t in the same spaces. I didn’t realize HipChat has completely changed their pricing and they now have a completely free offering. So now I’m trying to think of ways I can get it back in my life because I’ve missed it so much. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some stray observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I learned to cook bacon! Ruby for Good was an all-inclusive event, but in this type of environment catered food just won’t do. We divided meal responsibilities among teams and my team cooked breakfast for everyone on Saturday morning. It’s another great way to bring people together. I also learned that you can make large quantities of scrambled eggs in the oven. Except the oven we were using didn’t work very well so I’ll have to take their word for that one.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One thing I was pleasantly surprised by was the number of people there who attended or are currently attending code schools. The ones I talked to all spoke very highly of their experiences. And in a small world moment I ran into a friend I participated in Founder’s Institute with. He recently completed Dev Bootcamp and was preparing to start his first full-time programming job in D.C. on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I definitely recommend Ruby for Good to anyone in the future. This was the inaugural event and I certainly hope it continues. There was such a wide variety of projects, from documentation, to writing test suites, to full-blown applications, there was something for any skill level or interest.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Huge shout out to everyone on Team Pathway Homes! &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/alindeman&quot;&gt;Andy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/brandonlrice&quot;&gt;Brandon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bglusman&quot;&gt;Brian&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ecbailey&quot;&gt;Emily&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/jmaisu&quot;&gt;James&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/mad_typist&quot;&gt;Jessie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mepps&quot;&gt;Maggie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/melaniew&quot;&gt;Mel&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/RMalecky&quot;&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://alwaysbelearning.com/2014/08/05/ruby-for-good/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alwaysbelearning.com/2014/08/05/ruby-for-good/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Repeat Yourself</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The best way I’ve found to retain knowledge and truly learn is by repeating myself. I engrain practices in my head through repition and see parts in a new light each time. More often than not I don’t revisit projects or exercises though and want to make a better habit of that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I spent some time with the always helpful, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/josh_cheek&quot;&gt;Josh Cheek&lt;/a&gt;. Josh was in D.C. for a week and spent a couple of days helping me to learn and learn how to learn. You read that right. From time to time I go through materials on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theodinproject.com&quot;&gt;The Odin Project&lt;/a&gt;, which is a great, open-source (i.e. free as in beer), programming curriculum. It’s outlined similarly to many of the coding bootcamps that are growing in popularity and I definitely recommend checking it out. When Josh arrived I was just preparing to start a Ruby &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theodinproject.com/ruby-programming/advanced-building-blocks&quot;&gt;exercise&lt;/a&gt; that required me to write my own version of many of the common Enumerable methods. A bit of panic set in but Josh thought this was a great lesson and a great opportunity to try katas. A kata, in &lt;a href=&quot;&#39;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kata_(programming)&#39;&quot;&gt;programming terms&lt;/a&gt;, is improving your skills and knowledge through pracitice and repition. So in this case I would write all of my Enumerable mehods and then write them again and again, hopefully getting faster each time and understanding them better which will also lead to refactoring. Actually writing my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/britneywright/my_enumerable&quot;&gt;initial&lt;/a&gt; Enumerable methods took hours. Thankfully Josh is a very patient teach and by the end I felt like I really gained a much deeper understanding of enumerables. You can see my first completed kata here. Afterwards, I rewrote all of my methods one or two more times before moving on to adding more methods. I got stuck here and there, but fortunately I was able to talk them out with Josh and push on. Unfortunately I let other shiny objects distract me and I haven’t revisited &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/britneywright/my_enumerable_2&quot;&gt;this exercise&lt;/a&gt; in a couple of weeks. But yesterday something prompted me to remember it and the value it provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago I, along with my pair partner, started &lt;a href=&quot;http://railsgirlssummerofcode.org/&quot;&gt;Rails Girls Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt;. We’ll be working on two popular open source Ruby on Rails projects, BrowserCMS and Spree. BrowserCMS is a a content management system, for those unfamiliar with the CMS space, think Wordpress or Drupal, which are more commonly known, PHP-based, CMS platforms. Spree is an e-commerce platform. Our goal is to create a module for BrowserCMS that would make it easier to integrate Spree. We believe that this type of module would make it easier for developers to get started with them in a single project and could lead to increased use of both. So far we’ve focused on learning BrowserCMS by trying to build the basic features of an online store through the CMS (minus payment stuff). We had some hiccups at the start. Since BrowserCMS recently released a beta of their newest version a lot of the documentation is outdated so we’ve had to determine what instructions apply to us and what doesn’t as we’re building our sites. Over the past week I’ve been knocking items off our list of features we outlined as common to online bookstores. When we met yesterday though I realized that a lot of the approaches I took were not necessarily using BrowserCMS in the best way or weren’t the most efficient. For a moment I felt defeated, but then I thought back to the katas I did with the Enumerable methods. I realized that rather than just taking notes and moving on, this would be a great opportunity for me to go back through the features I’ve bult so far and do them again based on the discussions we had as a team. So that’s where I’m at now. About to start building version 2.0 of my pratice book store. My goal is to write my code more confidently this time, which to me means better and faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once I finish rebuilding my project to it’s most current feature-set I think I’ll revisit my enumerable methods and do a few more katas with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you tried katas, The Odin Project or any of the other projects and ideas I mentioned? Let me know. As always you can find me on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/britneywright&quot;&gt;@britneywright&lt;/a&gt; and here on my blog &lt;a href=&quot;http://alwaysbelearning.co&quot;&gt;Always Be Learning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To follow along with our Rails Girls Summer of Code project you can check out: &lt;a href=&quot;browserspree.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;browserspree.tumblr.com&lt;/a&gt;, follow us on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/browserspree&quot;&gt;@browserspree&lt;/a&gt;, or view our code on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/browserspree&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.     &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://alwaysbelearning.com/2014/07/15/repeat-yourself/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alwaysbelearning.com/2014/07/15/repeat-yourself/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yeah Baby, Yeah</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/2014/07/powers-meme.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Focus on the journey, not the destination. Joy is found not in finishing an activity but in doing it.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cynthialanel/status/486986287505604608&quot;&gt;@cynthialanel&lt;/a&gt; for this gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/britneywright/status/484905258909704192&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; last week about the importance of watching videos or reading blog posts in their entirety before going off to work on your own projects. I’m guilty of not doing this often and suffer the consequences. I spend hours looking to solve something, only to realize if I would’ve just watched two more minutes of a video or read a couple more paragraphs and that original resource would’ve solved what I was working on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 19:57:17 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://alwaysbelearning.com/jekyll/github/2014/07/09/dangerous/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alwaysbelearning.com/jekyll/github/2014/07/09/dangerous/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Blog Configuration</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal:&lt;/strong&gt; Setup second blog using Github Pages, Jekyll and a custom domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progress:&lt;/strong&gt; Completed, one day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve set up a number of personal websites and blogs over the years, but it seems that each time I do things a little bit differently. I moved on from wordpress at the beginning of the year for the simpler pastures of &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. Using my text editor to write my posts allows me to focus more on writing and less on all the other “stuff” that comes along with platforms like Wordpress. Pushing to Github is quick and easy, and also means everything you write is automatically backed up. And best of all, if you’re using a public repo it’s free. I’m slowly weaning myself off of paid hosting and finding it to be a much smoother experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub Project Pages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Migrating my first &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onebrokeb.com&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; was fairly straightforward since Github allows one User Pages site per account. I felt like it was possible to setup more than one blog, but wasn’t sure of the process. So today I spent a bit of time researching the blog setup and also if there would be any domain issues before I went out and purchased my new domain. From the GitHub documentation I determined that I needed to create my second blog as a Project Pages site. After one false start with setting up the repo properly I found and followed the initial steps outlined by &lt;a href=&quot;http://24ways.org/2013/get-started-with-github-pages/&quot;&gt;Anna Debenham&lt;/a&gt;. The unique thing about Project Page sites is that they are intended to contain project files and site files in the same repo, but in separate branches. Since I’m just plannig a standalone site I only needed the gh-pages branch in the repo. So when I got to the “Make gh-pages your default branch” part of Anna’s post I used a command line prompt provided by &lt;a href=&quot;http://feeding.cloud.geek.nz/posts/setting-default-git-branch-in-bare/&quot;&gt;François Marier&lt;/a&gt;. Then I continued through Anna’s post until just after the “jekyll new” part. She continues to go over creating individual files, but once Jekyll is installed it already includes the necessary files to get started and I wanted to finish my initial setup before customizing anything. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Custom domain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last part of my initial setup was the domain. I use a different domain registrar each time, with mixed results. Today I chose to go with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.namecheap.com&quot;&gt;Namecheap&lt;/a&gt; and I was pleasantly surprised by the simple process and clean interface. They didn’t have ads all over the place, or try to upsell me on a million things. It was straightforward and a good price of only about $15 for the domain and they include Whois privacy at no extra cost. The final step was creating the CNAME file in my repo and changing the A records in Namecheap to point my new domain, alwaysbelearning.co to the blog. After everything was deployed and configured it seemed to only take a few minutes for the site to load on the domain. Victory!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next steps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then I’ve updated the __config.yml file with my basic site info. I also wrote an about page and created my first inspirational graphic for the site using the nifty tool &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canva.com&quot;&gt;Canva&lt;/a&gt;, and wrote my first posts. Hopefully over the next week I’ll find time to work on the site aesthics, but I really plan on doing on going experiments with the look of the site as I experiment with different front-end tools and techniques. But all in all, not bad for a day’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- B&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2014 19:57:17 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://alwaysbelearning.com/jekyll/github/2014/06/28/new-blog-configuration/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alwaysbelearning.com/jekyll/github/2014/06/28/new-blog-configuration/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello Universe!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal&lt;/strong&gt;: Create a space to talk about my ongoing learning affair with development and technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progress&lt;/strong&gt;: First post&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re off! Check out my &lt;a href=&quot;http://alwaysbelearning.com/about&quot;&gt;About&lt;/a&gt; page for the full run down of why I created this blog. But the short story is that I finally feel comfortable enough talking tech that I actually want to write about what I’m doing and what I’m learning. Of course there’s the standard “hope someone else out there will benefit” goal, but really at it’s core this space is for me. I’ll be winning, losing, making mistakes, learning from my mistakes. On the good days I’ll reflect on how far I’ve come and on the bad days I’ll reflect on how far I’ve come. Sounds like an all upside proposition to me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in case you were wondering where the inspiration for the blog name came from. I have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23CodeNewbies&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;#CodeNewbies&lt;/a&gt; Twitter chat to thank for that. In a moment of genius I tweeted the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/britneywright/statuses/481974760034013184&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/2014/06/abl-tweet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Focus on the journey, not the destination. Joy is found not in finishing an activity but in doing it.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a name and new blog idea were born. Enjoy the ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- B&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2014 18:57:17 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://alwaysbelearning.com/2014/06/28/welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alwaysbelearning.com/2014/06/28/welcome/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
